<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A blovdy fight at Dublin in Ireland, between the Marquesse of Ormond, and Col. Jones, and a list of the officers and souldiers killed and taken on both sides, with the manner of the fight, and the Lord Moon's revolting from the Parliament to the Prince, and joyning his horse with the said Marquesse; together with Col. Trevor, Col. Yearmond, and divers of Sir Thomas Armstrong's horse, deserting of Col. Jones, and declaring for the Kings of Scots; &amp; the uniting of the Irish armies against the Parliament.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 11 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 6 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A76864</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B3237</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E563_6</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206074</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865262</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865262</idno>
            <idno type="VID">165251</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A76864)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 165251)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 87:E563[6])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A blovdy fight at Dublin in Ireland, between the Marquesse of Ormond, and Col. Jones, and a list of the officers and souldiers killed and taken on both sides, with the manner of the fight, and the Lord Moon's revolting from the Parliament to the Prince, and joyning his horse with the said Marquesse; together with Col. Trevor, Col. Yearmond, and divers of Sir Thomas Armstrong's horse, deserting of Col. Jones, and declaring for the Kings of Scots; &amp; the uniting of the Irish armies against the Parliament.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Williamson, and are to be sold at the Royall Exchange in Corn-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "July. 6.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Ormonde, James Butler, --  Duke of, 1610-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Commonwealth and Protectorate, 1649-1660 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:165251:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 98 -->
            <p>A BLOVDY FIGHT AT DVBLIN in IRELAND, BETWEEN The Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and Col. <hi>Jones,</hi> and a Liſt of the Officers and Souldiers killed and taken on both ſides, with the manner of the fight, and the Lord <hi>Moon</hi>'s revolting from the <hi>Parliament</hi> to the <hi>Prince,</hi> and joyning his horſe with the ſaid Marqueſſe; Together with Col. <hi>Trevor,</hi> Col. <hi>Yearmond,</hi> and divers of Sir <hi>Thomas Armſtrong</hi>'s horſe, deſerting of Col. Jones, and declaring for the King of <hi>Scots;</hi> &amp; the uniting of the Iriſh Armies againſt the Parliament.</p>
            <figure>
               <head>
                  <date>
                     <add>July .6.</add>
                  </date>
               </head>
               <figDesc>depiction of battle at Dublin, Ireland</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON, Printed for <hi>R. Williamſon,</hi> and are to be ſold at the Royall Exchange in Corn-hill. 1649</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:165251:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 99 -->
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="account_of_battle">
            <pb facs="tcp:165251:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 100 -->
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:165251:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 100 -->
            <head>A GREAT FIGHT AT <hi>Dublin</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> between the Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and Col. <hi>Jones,</hi> with a Liſt of the chief Officers killed and taken on both ſides.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He Marq. of <hi>Ormond,</hi> and the Lord <hi>Inchiquin</hi> with 14000 Horſe and Foot, have intrench<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed themſelves (in many places) within Sacre ſhot of the Walls, and by their ſtrong alla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rums keeps us in continuall action: the laſt night their Pioneers wrought exceeding hard, and raiſed an half Moon within musket ſhot of the North Port, where was placed about 200 musketiers, and four pieces of Ord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance; it was contrived very artificially and ſtrong, with a running Trench from their frontier incampings: this mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:165251:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 101 -->we ſallyed out upon them, with a reſolution to beat them off from the ſaid Fort; but finding too much oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion retreated to our Redout, which was within Piſtoll ſhot thereof; about 4 of the clock ſeverall parties of horſe and foot were drawn forth on both ſides, who engaged each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and after a ſharp conflict diſputed with great gallantry the enemy retreated, and having a Reſerve ready at hand our men durſt not embrace the purſuit, but returned Victors with 7 priſoners, 9 horſes, and left dead and wounded upon the place about 15 with the loſſe of 9 men, which the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my in the night time ſet off and buryed.</p>
            <p>In one of our former Sallies, Capt. <hi>Glyn</hi> with a party of 30 horſe fell upon a deſperate party of the Beſiegers, and after a ſharp diſpute took
<list>
                  <head>priſoners</head>
                  <item>Lieut. Colonell Dungan.</item>
                  <item>Major Williams.</item>
                  <item>Captain O Brian.</item>
                  <item>Captain Talbot.</item>
                  <item>Lieutenant Ogleby.</item>
                  <item>Cornet Bembrick.</item>
                  <item>And about 12 <hi>Troopers.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>killed</head>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Major Dungan,</hi> brother to the aforeſaid Lieu. Col.         <hi>Dungan.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>Captain Willkinſon.</item>
                  <item>Quartermaster Mackart.</item>
                  <item>Corporall Pemerton.</item>
                  <item>And about 7 men.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Of Col. Jones party
<list>
                  <head>killed</head>
                  <item>Quartermaster Smith, Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termaster to his own troop.</item>
                  <item>Corporal Reyner.</item>
                  <item>And 3 troopers.</item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <head>wounded,</head>
                  <item>Lieutenant Brabſon.</item>
                  <item>Cornet Jenkins.</item>
                  <item>Corporall Armstrong.</item>
                  <item>And 4 or 5 private men.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>We are ſeldome out of action, and our renowned Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is infinitely tyred out, having not been in his bed theſe ten nights, and moſt part of the day is viewing the enemy, or repairing our Works and Fortifications, and planting
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:165251:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 101 -->pieces round the Line: the Iriſh Officers have made choice of a great Epiſcopal Biſhop to be their chief Engineer, who acts and ſtudies very politikely both ſpiritually and tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porally.</p>
            <p>Our condition being dangerous, cauſeth fadneſſe unto us, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very day the enemy being ſtrong, and our men many of them perfidious, moſt diſhonourable, betraying their truſt, the Lord <hi>Moon</hi> with a gallant troop of horſe, is gone to the enemy, who upon a ſalley forth, pretended to engage againſt them, but when he was within piſtoll ſhot, faced about, and fell upon a party of our own horſe, a troop of Sir <hi>Thomas Armſtrongs</hi> run away alſo, and Col. <hi>Yeamonds</hi> troop moul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter away, and deſert us extreamly; the enemy hath beſieged what Gariſons we have not ſlighted, Drogedan is in great danger of loſing, many others will be loſt, for we cannot ſtir from this City to help them without better ſtore of Forces for their relief. Col. <hi>Trevor</hi> hath likewiſe deſerted us, and is gone to the enemy, where he entred into proteſtation to the Marqueſſe, declaring, <hi>That he would uſe all the intereſt that poſſible he could, for the calling away of his Regiment, and that he was aſſured of their coming, with many othhrs alſo,</hi> the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my continues drawing nearer this place, hindering all Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>k<gap reason="illegible: damage" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s, ſo that we are brought very low, every thing being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary dear, and the Inhabitants ſo taxed for ſupport of the Souldiers, as that they will be undone. God in mercy look upon us, and help us.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>From bleeding Dublin<date>the fourth of <hi>July,</hi> 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:165251:5"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 102 -->
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VPon mature deliberation of the preſent tranſaction of affairs, in reference to the proceedings between Prince and People, I thought requiſite to illuſtre the demonſtration thereof, to your publike view, by diſplaying Truth in its <gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpotted Colours under the Banner of Impartiality, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting thoſe things that are of greateſt concernment, and ſaid to be the main Object on which the Eyes of all Europe are now fixed upon, which by a ſerious glance, over theſe enſuing lines, the ſplendor thereof appears as followeth:</p>
            <p>The Parliament of Scotland ſeem to be exceedingly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>contented at the tranſaction of affairs in England, and at the preſent proceedings of their young King (as they ſay) and have ſent a Meſſage to the queen of Sweden, with a large Narative of what they did joyntly with the Parliament of England, where they fell off, how they deteſt their late pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings, in reference to the executing of their late Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign Lord the King, how their young King is ſeduc'd by evill Councell, and from thence hath not given their Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſioners ſatisfaction neceſſary for his own and the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes Weal, deſiring her Majeſty to ſend an Embaſſie unto him, to perſwade him to a Condeſcenſion, and ſpeedy A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement; <hi>but this ſeems a myſtery to many, divers concei<gap reason="illegible" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ing it to be one of</hi> Jockies <hi>new Riddles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For it is frequently ſaid, that the Articles of Agreement are already concluded of, and that they begin to caſt this Miſt, only to obſcure tho eye-ſight of the Engliſh, until they have brought to maturity their deſign in hand, for the rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of 15000 Horſe and Foot to joyn with the 5000 alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy i<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Arms, which they pretend to be for the ſafety of that kingdom againſt forraign Invaſion. Only Gen. Leſley de<gap reason="illegible" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ies the Generalſhip, the Marq. of Argyle its conceived will be choſen Commander in chief.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:165251:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 102 -->
His Excellency Generall Leſley being deſired to deliver up the ſtrong Caſtle of Edenburgh, returned anſwer, That he was reſolved to keepe it for the ſucceſſion of thoſe who had entruſted him, meaning the late <hi>King of Great Brittain, Charles the first.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Parliament are very private in their debates, and (ſay ſome) are reſolved to ſhake the foundation of Hereſie.</p>
            <p>We hear; That the declared King of Scotland, accompa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nied by the Prince of Orange, half way to Antwerp, was met by ſome eminent perſons appointed for that purpoſe, who preſented him from the Arch Duke, with a moſt ſumptuous Caroach ſtudded with maſſie ſilver, and fix gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lant Flanders horſes of great value, ſuch as a King of bare Scotland was never maſter of before, probably Genit's or of the Nerpolitan race, when he was come to Antwerp the Magiſtrates conducted him to the high ſtreet, call'd Mair and lodged him in a ſtarely Pallace, he remain'd in Ant<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>werp two dayes and two nights during which time he was welcommed with all imaginable expreſſions of honour and reſpect, and at the Caſtle, which he had the honour to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vited to, he wes entertain'd as if the King of Spain had been, there himſelf, he went to ſee the Town and the rarieties of the Churches; which as anciently, ſo now exceeds all others in thoſe Countries, if not in Chriſtendome, at his departure, happy was he that could kiſſe his cloke, which by accident hung out of the Coach as he paſt away: Fryday morning he departed hence, having dined at Machlin he came to Bruxels that night, where he was, as all along, moſt largely welcom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, and royally entertained, and had been more, had not his comming been at a time when the Arch-Duke was ſo deep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly engaged in the relief of his deareſt Miſtris Cambray, which as ſome Letters come at this inſtant to this place ſay is to the great prejudice of the French, the certeinty where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of expect by the next.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:165251:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 103 -->
Lievtenant Collonel Hobſon is come to Edenburgh, his buſineſſe is variouſly ſpoken, ſome whiſper that he deſires paſsage for ſome to go for Ireland, others to make way for ſome farther overture from Parl of England, what ever it is he is looked upon with a jealous eye.</p>
            <p>From the Iſle of Man our Intelligence ſaith, That Sir <hi>Lewis Dives,</hi> and many other Engliſh Gallants, have made great preparations in that Iſland againſt the Parliament of England, and are reſolved for Ireland, to aſſiſt the Marqueſſe of Ormond, and ſtrengthen the ſiege at Dublin; from whence it is ſaid, that the Parliaments party is reduced to Dublin, Dredah, Dundale, Trim, and London-Derry, the firſt &amp; laſt being beſieged; by Ormonds coming up to Dublin he hath got the greateſt part of five Counties from Col. Jones, which afforded him many thouſand pounds contribution.</p>
            <p>We hear that Gen. <hi>Oneal</hi> is united with <hi>Ormond,</hi> and hath ſtrengthned his Camp with 4000 Foot, the E. of <hi>Clanrickard</hi> and Col. <hi>Monro</hi> is expected there with another Brigade, by which means they will be both potent and powerfull, the Army amounting to above 20000 Horſe and Foot.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>Cheſter <date>5. July, 1649.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
